Guide to the Gil Whitaker academic papers, 1970-2004 UA 105
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Gil Whitaker academic papers
1970-2004
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Whitaker, Gilbert R., Jr.
UA 105
8 Linear Feet (8 boxes)
The collection consists of papers documenting the professional activity of Gilbert R. Whitaker, Jr. from the 1970's through 2004, primarily at the University of Michigan and Rice University. Included are personal day books, correspondence, newsclips, speeches, and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Gilbert R. Whitaker, Jr. earned a B.A. in economics from Rice University in 1953. From 1953 to 1956 he was an ensign in the U.S. Navy, serving as a gunnery officer on a destroyer. He then began graduate study in economics, first at Southern Methodist University and then at the University of Wisconsin, Madison, where he earned an M.S. in 1958 and a Ph.D. in 1961. His major in economics was theory, and his minor, statistics. In 1959-60 he had a Ford Foundation Dissertation Fellowship.
Dr. Whitaker's academic appointments were, chronologically, at Northwestern University (1960-1966); Washington University, St. Louis (1966-1976); Texas Christian University, Fort Worth (1976-1978); University of Michigan, Ann Arbor (1979-1997); and Rice University (1997-2005). At Texas Christian he was dean of the M. J. Neeley School of Business, and he joined the University of Michigan as dean of the School of Business Administration. There he rose to become provost and executive vice president for academic affairs. After retiring from the University of Michigan, he became dean and H. Joe Nelson III Professor of Business Economics at the Jesse H. Jones Graduate School of Management at Rice University.
In addition to his work at these universities, Dr. Whitaker served in a variety of other educational organizations, including the University of West Indies, Kingston, Jamaica (external examiner, 1975-1978), the University of Wisconsin (system advisor, 1986 and 1995), the American Assembly of Collegiate Schools of Business (1977-1991), Consortium for Graduate Study in Management (director, 1971-1976; council of deans, 1985-1990), the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill (chairman, visitation team for graduate program of the Graduate School of Business, 1987), Yale University (chair, accreditation review team for the Yale School of Management, 1998), Case Western Reserve University (chairman of the review committee for the Weatherhead School of Management, 1999), JSTOR (board of trustees and secretary/treasurer, 1995-2002), The Washington Campus Program (director, 1979-1988; vice chairman, 1983-1985; chairman, 1985-1988), Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges (1993-2004), Forum for the Future of Higher Education (board of directors, 1997-2004), and The Learning Alliance (consultant, 2003-2004).
Dr. Whitaker's experience included contributions to the following private corporations: Handleman Company (Director, 1989-1999), Lincoln National Corporation (Director, 1986-2002), Structural Dynamics Research Corporation (Director, 1986-2001), Johnson Controls, Inc. (Director, 1986-2001), and Westlake Chemical (Director, 2004-2007).
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of papers documenting the professional activity of Gilbert R. Whitaker, Jr. from the 1970's through 2004, primarily at the University of Michigan and Rice University. Included are personal day books, correspondence, newsclippings, speeches, and photographs.
Access Restrictions
Restrictions apply to some folders within this collection as noted at the folder level. Contact woodson@rice.edu for assistance.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was a gift donated by Gilbert R. Whitaker, Jr.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges
Document Types
clippings (information artifacts); photographs; speeches; letters (correspondence); daybooks
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University -- history.
- Series I: University of Michigan, 209715
  Restrictions Apply
  Restrictions apply to folder within this series: - Speech: Budget Presentation to Regents - Speech: Budget Presentation (95/95 School Year)
  - University of Michigan: Commencement Programs, 209716 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - University of Michigan Publications, 209717 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - University of Michigan Business School Publications, 209718 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - University of Michigan Speeches, 209719 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - University of Michigan Presentations, 209720 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - University of Michigan Legal Paperwork, 209721 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - University of Michigan Recognition and Awards, 209722 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Documents Regarding Michigan Appointments, 209723 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - University of Michigan - Provost Appointment Terms and Conditions, 209725 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - University of Michigan Library, 209726 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - University of Michigan Visiting Committee, 209727 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - University of Michigan United Way Campaigns, 209729 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - University of Michigan Alumni, 209731 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - University of Michigan - Senete Assembly, Sept. 1992, 209732 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Comments on Gilbert Whitaker from Provost and Staff of University of Michigan, 209734 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - University of Michigan Photos, 209736 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Michigan Press Releases, 209738 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The Whitaker Fellowship, 209739 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Gerald R. Ford Library Committee, 209740 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - University of Michigan - Correspondence 1970s, 209742 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - University of Michigan - Correspondence 1980s, 209743 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - University of Michigan - Correspondence Early 1990s, 209745 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - University of Michigan - Correspondence/Congratulations of Appointment as Provost, 209746 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - University of Michigan - Correspondence 1994/1995 School Year, 209748 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - University of Michigan - Related Correspondence 2000s, 209750 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - University of Michigan - Correspondence - Karl A. Hill, 209751 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - University of Michigan - Correspondence - Edna Lacy, 209753 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - University of Michigan - Speech Related Correspondence, 209754 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Speech: Michigan Graduate School of Business Administration, 03/28/1979; 209755 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Speech: Michigan Faculty, 03/29/1982; 209883 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Speech: MBA Orientation, 09/07/1982; 209884 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Speech: NY Media, 11/14/1982; 209885 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Speech: AACSB, 11/1982; 209886 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Speech: Commencement 1983, 209887 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Speech: MBA Matriculation, 09/02/1986; 209888 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Speech: MBA Orientation (Fall 1987), 209889 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Speech: Ann Arbor Rotary, 01/20/1988; 209890 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Speech: AACSB Annual Meeting (1989), 209891 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Speech: Michigan Faculty Retreat, 09/08/1989; 209892 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Speech: LS&A Faculty Meeting, 09/10/1990; 209893 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Speech: Michigan Freshman Convocation (1990), 09/04/1990; 209894 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Speech: Michigan Cost Task Force and Budget Priorities Committee, 02/15/1990; 209895 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Speech: School of Music Scholarship Night, 10/27/1990; 209896 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Speech: Music Auditorium Gifts Committee and Detriot Club, 11/05/1990; 209897 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Speech: Warner Retirement Reception, 12/03/1990; 209898 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Speech: University of Michigan Senate Assembly, 12/10/1990; 209899 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Speech: Student Alumni Council, 1/27/1991; 209900 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Speech: Information Technology General Council, 01/31/1991; 209901 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Speech: IAIMS Site Visit, 02/11/1991; 209902 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Speech: Regarding Women's Issues, 02/11/1991; 209903 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Speech: Copernicus Dinner, 04/05/1991; 209904 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Speech: Qualtec, 04/10/1991; 209905 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Speech: University of Michigan Senate Assembly, 04/15/1991; 209906 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Speech: AAUP Michigan Chapter, 05/14/1991; 209907 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Speech: Testimony Before Appropriations Committee, 05/14/1991; 209908 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Speech: Budget Presentation to Regents, 07/18/1991; 209909 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Speech: Executive Management Quality Workshop, 08/26/1991; 209910 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Speech: University of Michigan Senate Assembly, 09/16/1991; 209911 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Speech: School of Dentistry, 09/26/1991; 209912 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Speech: Stanford Forum, 11/05/1991; 209913 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Speech: Sarah Goddard Power Award, 01/23/1992; 209914 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Speech: Management Institute, 01/24/1992; 209915 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Speech: Israel Conference Day, 02/02/1992; 209916 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Speech: MSRB II Groundbreaking, 02/05/1992; 209917 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Speech: House Committee on Colleges and Universities, 02/04/1992; 209918 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Speech: Annual Michigan School Testing Conference, 02/02/1992; 209919 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Speech: Saturn Award Ceremony, 03/31/1992; 209920 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Speech: University Club of Dearborn, 05/21/1992; 209921 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Speech: Total Quality Conference, 06/03/1992; 209922 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Speech: Business Institute on Finance, 02/05/1993; 209923 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Speech: Goldern Apple Award Host, 03/29/1993; 209924 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Speech: Phi Kappa Phi, 04/29/1993; 209925 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Speech: Alumni Association Board of Directors, 209926 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Speech: University Club of Fort Wayne, 05/12/1993; 209927 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Speech: University of Michigan Senate Assembly, 05/17/1993; 209928 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Speech: Town & Gown Rotary, 06/23/1993; 209929 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Speech: University of Michigan Senate Assembly, 09/20/1993; 209930 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Speech: Biennial Breakfast, 10/01/1993; 209931 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Speech: Korean and Taiwanese Alumni, 11/1993; 209932 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Speech: Business Institute on Finance, 02/04/1994; 209933 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Speech: Senate Higher Education Subcommittee, 02/11/1994; 209934 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Speech: Accounting and Budgeting Views, 04/04/1994; 209935 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Speech: University of Michigan Senate Assembly, 05/16/1994; 209936 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Speech: Budget Presentation (95/95 School Year), 07/14/1994; 209937 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Speech: ISAGA Group, 07/24/1994; 209938 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Speech: Faculty Orientation, 09/01/1994; 209939 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Speech: University of Michigan Senate Assembly, 09/26/1994; 209940 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Speech: AAUP Panel, 02/09/1995; 209941 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Speech: Univesity of Michigan Senate Assembly, 05/15/1995; 209942 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - University of Michigan Photographs, 209943 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - University of Michigan Business Cards, 209944 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - University of Michigan Interviews, 209945 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - University of Michigan Name Badges, 209946 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Oversized Photographs and Awards, 209998 (Drawer 148, Folder 24)
- Series II: Rice University, 209947
  Restrictions apply to some folders within in series.
  - Jones Graduate School Budget Documents, 209948 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Budget Documents (FY 2006), 209949 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Jones Graduate School: General Documents, 209950 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Jones Graduate School: Councils and Board of Directors, 209951 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Jones Graduate School: Faculty, 209952 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Search Nominations, 209953 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Distinguished Alumni Award, 209954 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Rice Photographs, 209955 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Rice Honors and Awards, 209956 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Rice Commencements, 209957 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Recommendations, 209958 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence on Appointment At Rice University (1997), 209959 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Rice Faculty Meetings, 209960 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Rice Business Education Advisory Committee, 209961 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Rice Managerial Studies, 209962 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Jones Graduate School of Executive Development, 209963 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Biographical Documents, 209964 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Rice Admissions Interviews, 209965 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Corresspondence: Unknown Sender or Recipient, 209966 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: A, 209967 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: B, 209968 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: C, 209969 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: D, 209970 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: F, 209971 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: G, 209972 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: H, 209973 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence: J, 209974 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence: K, 209975 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: L, 209976 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence: M, 209977 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence: O, 209978 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence: P, 209979 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence: R, 209980 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence: S, 209981 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence: T, 209982 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence: U, 209983 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence: V, 209984 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence: W, 209985
  - Correspondence: Y-Z, 209986 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Rice Speeches, 209987 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Jones Graduate School of Management Groundbreaking Event, 209988 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Jones Graduate School Events and Publications, 209989 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Jones Graduate School History, 209990 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Jones Journal, 209991 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Rice Newsclippings, 209992 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Rice Legal Paperwork, 209993 (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Series III: Other Academic Institutions, 209995
  - Cleary College, 209996 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Classen High School Alumni Association, 209997 (Box 4, Folder 40)
- Series IV: Awards, Recognition and Newsclippings, 209999
  - Certificates, 210000 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Newsclips 1970s, 210001 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Newsclips 1980s, 210002 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Newsclips 1990-1993 (copies), 210003 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Newsclips 1994-1997 (copies), 210004 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Newsclips (1990), 210005 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Newsclips (1991), 210006 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Newsclips (1992), 210007 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Newsclips (1993), 210008 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Newsclips (1994), 210009 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Newsclips (1995), 210010 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Series V: Personal Materials and Daybooks, 210011
  - Conference Materials, 210012 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous Personal Items, 210013 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Saudi Arabia, 210014 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Personal Daybooks and Diaries (1978-1982), 210015 (Box 6, Envelope 5)
  - Personal Daybooks and Diaries (1983-1990, 1996), 210016 (Box 8, Envelope 1)
  - Personal Daybooks and Diaries (1999-2003), 210017 (Box 7)
- Series VI: Corporate Involvement, 210018
  - Detroit Advertising, 210019 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Corporate Involvement, 210020 (Box 8, Folder 3)